<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SWAT on  </title>
    <link>/tags/swat/</link>
    <description>Recent content in SWAT on  </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/swat/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Tidy Tuesday Hydrology Version: Tidying Up SWAT Outputs</title>
      <link>/post/2018-10-16-tidy-swat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-10-16-tidy-swat/</guid>
      <description>Background I recently participated in Thomas Mock’s Tidy Tuesday R challenge with other members of the NC State University R Learning Group. It was a lot of fun and after participating, I felt motivated to share what I’ve been doing to tidy up my own data sets.
Specifically, I’ve been working with collaborator, Kelly Suttles, to tidy up model outputs from the Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT). SWAT is a hydrologic model used to predict daily and monthly streamflow and water quality at the watershed-scale.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sociohydrology in Western North Carolina</title>
      <link>/project/nc-sociohydro-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/nc-sociohydro-project/</guid>
      <description>Collaborators B Cutts (NC State), R Emanuel (NC State), K Martin (NC State), KM Suttles (USFS), J Vose (USFS), D Wear (USFS), J Coulston (USFS)
Timeline 2017-current
Project Goal The goal of this project is to combine past and future hydrology model (i.e., Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT)) outputs with demographics data to create maps and prioritize climate change preparation and adaptation strategies for especially vulnerable communities in Western North Carolina&amp;rsquo;s Upper Yadkin-Pee Dee Watershed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>