<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>  on  </title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in   on  </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Using tibbletime::rollify with USGS Streamgage Data</title>
      <link>/post/2018-08-04-usgs-rollify/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Aug 2018 21:12:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-08-04-usgs-rollify/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div id=&#34;background&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While attending rstudio::conf 2018, I heard about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/tibbletime/tibbletime.pdf&#34;&gt;tibbletime package&lt;/a&gt; developed by Davis Vaughan and Matt Dancho for analysis of time series data. In his &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rstudio.com/resources/videos/the-future-of-time-series-and-financial-analysis-in-the-tidyverse/&#34;&gt;conference talk&lt;/a&gt;, Davis Vaughan presented several business/finance examples to showcase &lt;code&gt;tibbletime&lt;/code&gt;’s functionality and mentioned a few, general non-business applications at the end of his talk. I couldn’t help but think about how this package might be especially helpful for environmental scientists working with time series data. I really liked &lt;code&gt;rollify()&lt;/code&gt;, which could be used to create and apply custom moving window functions (e.g., &lt;code&gt;mean()&lt;/code&gt;) to time series data; where the size of the window (e.g., 3 days) could also be specified. I was aware of &lt;code&gt;movingAve()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;movingDiff()&lt;/code&gt; functions in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.usgs.gov/of/2015/1202/downloads/appendix1.pdf&#34;&gt;smwrBase package&lt;/a&gt; developed by the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), which calculate moving averages and differences, respectively. However, &lt;code&gt;rollify()&lt;/code&gt; seemed like it had a more flexibility; it could take a rolling standard deviation, a rolling ratio of two functions, or a custom function designed. The possibilities are endless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shortly after the conference, I also heard about the &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/dataRetrieval/dataRetrieval.pdf&#34;&gt;dataRetrieval package&lt;/a&gt; developed by the USGS. This package allows users to import USGS streamflow data (and any other data associated with &lt;a href=&#34;https://water.usgs.gov/nsip/definition9.html&#34;&gt;USGS streamgages&lt;/a&gt;) directly into R. Very exciting!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;goals-of-this-post&#34; class=&#34;section level1&#34;&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Goals of this Post&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all sounded so amazing and I had to try it out, which brings me to the goals of this blog post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;code&gt;dataRetrieval&lt;/code&gt; package to download streamflow data for two USGS streamgages into R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use the &lt;code&gt;tibbletime&lt;/code&gt; package (along with other &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; packages) to aggregate and plot these data for different time periods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/kghopkin?lang=en&#34;&gt;Dr. Kristina Hopkins&lt;/a&gt; at the USGS in Raleigh, NC for sharing her &lt;code&gt;dataRetrieval&lt;/code&gt; code!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First let’s load the R libraries that we’ll need to run the code in this post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tidyverse)
library(lubridate)
library(tibbletime)
library(dataRetrieval)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before downloading the data, you’ll have to specify a desired date range and look up the USGS streamgage identification number(s) for streamgage(s) of interest. To find these identification numbers you can go to the USGS &lt;a href=&#34;https://waterdata.usgs.gov/nwis/inventory&#34;&gt;Water of the Nation website&lt;/a&gt;. I looked up the numbers for sites near Durham, NC. For this post, I chose two: Eno River at Hillsborough, NC (#02085000) and Eno River at Durham, NC (#02085070). The Hillsborough site is upstream of Durham and is surrounded by less urban development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# define start and end dates
start_date &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;2017-01-01&amp;quot;
end_date &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;2018-01-01&amp;quot;

# define sites (you can also just use one site here)
site_numbers &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;02085070&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;02085000&amp;quot;)

# save site info to a variable so we can look at it later
site_info &amp;lt;- readNWISsite(site_numbers)

# look at site info
site_info$station_nm
## [1] &amp;quot;ENO RIVER AT HILLSBOROUGH, NC&amp;quot; &amp;quot;ENO RIVER NEAR DURHAM, NC&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we need to figure out what parameter code is associated with streamflow (i.e., discharge). To figure this out, we can save &lt;code&gt;parameterCdFile&lt;/code&gt; to a variable named &lt;code&gt;parameter_code_metadata&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;View(parameter_code_metadata)&lt;/code&gt; it to see the parameter code look-up table in RStudio. We can even search this file using the filter search (in the &lt;code&gt;View()&lt;/code&gt; window that pops up).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# look for parameters you want
parameter_code_metadata &amp;lt;- parameterCdFile

# we want discharage in cubic feet per second which is code &amp;quot;00060&amp;quot;
my_parameter_code &amp;lt;- &amp;quot;00060&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After doing this, we see that 00060 is the code for discharge in cubic feet per second (cfs). Now we’re ready to download streamflow data!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;discharge_raw &amp;lt;- readNWISuv(site_numbers, 
                            my_parameter_code, 
                            tz=&amp;#39;America/Jamaica&amp;#39;, 
                            start_date, end_date)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s tidy the data up a bit. We’ll change some of the column names so they make more sense later to us, add a column with the site name, and select only the most important columns. If you are using this for something more formal, you will want to do some QA/QC by checking out the discharge_code column. You can read more about what these codes mean &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.waterdata.usgs.gov/output-formats&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;discharge = discharge_raw %&amp;gt;%
  select(site_number = site_no, 
         date_time = dateTime,
         discharge_cfs = X_00060_00000,
         discharge_code = X_00060_00000_cd,
         time_zone = tz_cd) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(site_name = case_when(
    site_number == &amp;quot;02085000&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;eno_rv_hillsb&amp;quot;,
    site_number == &amp;quot;02085070&amp;quot; ~ &amp;quot;eno_rv_durham&amp;quot;)) %&amp;gt;%
  select(site_name, date_time, discharge_cfs)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;head()&lt;/code&gt;, we see that we’ve downloaded 15-min intervals of streamflow data for both sites. Let’s say we need daily discharge data to calibrate a hydrology model. We can aggregate the 15-min data to daily data pretty easily using &lt;code&gt;tidyverse&lt;/code&gt; functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# look at discharge
head(discharge, n = 10)
##        site_name           date_time discharge_cfs
## 1  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 00:00:00          9.68
## 2  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 00:15:00          9.68
## 3  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 00:30:00          9.68
## 4  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 00:45:00          9.68
## 5  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 01:00:00          9.68
## 6  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 01:15:00          9.68
## 7  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 01:30:00          9.32
## 8  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 01:45:00          9.32
## 9  eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 02:00:00          9.32
## 10 eno_rv_hillsb 2017-01-01 02:15:00          9.32

# calculate daily average discharage
discharge_daily &amp;lt;- discharge %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(year = year(date_time), 
         month = month(date_time),
         day = day(date_time)) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(date = ymd(paste0(year, &amp;quot;-&amp;quot;, month, &amp;quot;-&amp;quot;, day))) %&amp;gt;%
  select(site_name, date, discharge_cfs) %&amp;gt;%
  group_by(site_name, date) %&amp;gt;%
  summarize(avg_daily_discharge_cfs = mean(discharge_cfs))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s try plotting the daily hydrograph (i.e., average daily discharge vs time) for both sites!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ggplot(data = discharge_daily) +
  geom_line(aes(x = date, y = avg_daily_discharge_cfs, color = site_name)) +
  facet_wrap(~site_name, nrow = 2, ncol = 1) +
  ylab(&amp;quot;Average Daily Discharge (cfs)&amp;quot;) +
  theme(panel.grid.major = element_blank(),
        panel.grid.minor = element_blank(),
        panel.background = element_blank(),
        axis.line = element_line(colour = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;),
        axis.text.x = element_text(angle = 90, vjust = 0.5, hjust = 1))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2018-08-04-usgs-rollify_files/figure-html/plotting%20daily%20data-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As expected, we see that the two sites mimic one another over this one year time period. Remember, the Eno River at Hillsborough site is upstream of the Eno River at Durham site. We also see that the Eno River at Durham site (top, red line) has some higher peaks than the Eno River at Hillborough site (bottom, teal line). This also makes sense since the Durham site is surrounded by more urbanized land than the Hillsborough site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so let’s get back to the &lt;code&gt;tibbletime&lt;/code&gt; package. What if we want to compare different time spans? That is, not just daily, but maybe hourly or half day. First we have to define our rolling functions and their associated time spans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this post, let’s create half hour, hourly, half day, and day rolls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;# create rollify functions
mean_roll_30min &amp;lt;- rollify(mean, window = 2)
mean_roll_1hr &amp;lt;- rollify(mean, window = 4)
mean_roll_12hr &amp;lt;- rollify(mean, window = 48)
mean_roll_1d &amp;lt;- rollify(mean, window = 96)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post we’ll focus on using the mean in our rolling functions but I can think of several other functions that might be useful for streamgage data lovers: difference, standard deviation, or maybe even the ratio between two calculations. You could even write your own function and roll that. Pretty flexible, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After you you write the function &lt;code&gt;my_roll_function &amp;lt;- rollify(&amp;lt;function&amp;gt;, window = &amp;lt;row span&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt; then you can call &lt;code&gt;my_roll_function(&amp;lt;original data column&amp;gt;)&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code&gt;mutate()&lt;/code&gt; to create a new column. Depending on the function you’re using, you could maybe even do a nested roll based on a previous column you created. This seems helpful if you’re taking differences or summations across different time scales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s roll (our data)! :D&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;discharge_roll &amp;lt;- discharge %&amp;gt;%
  group_by(site_name) %&amp;gt;%
  mutate(
    halfhr_avg_discharge_cfs = mean_roll_30min(discharge_cfs),
    hourly_avg_discharge_cfs = mean_roll_1hr(discharge_cfs),
    twelvehr_avg_discharge_cfs = mean_roll_12hr(discharge_cfs), 
    daily_avg_discharge_cfs = mean_roll_1d(discharge_cfs)) %&amp;gt;%
  na.omit()

# use na.omit() to delete some of the first cells in the dataframe that are NA&amp;#39;s due to rolling&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;head(discharge_roll, n = 10) 
## # A tibble: 10 x 7
## # Groups:   site_name [1]
##    site_name date_time           discharge_cfs halfhr_avg_disc…
##    &amp;lt;chr&amp;gt;     &amp;lt;dttm&amp;gt;                      &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;            &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;
##  1 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-01 23:45:00          12.1             12.1
##  2 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 00:00:00          12.1             12.1
##  3 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 00:15:00          11.6             11.8
##  4 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 00:30:00          11.6             11.6
##  5 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 00:45:00          11.6             11.6
##  6 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 01:00:00          12.1             11.8
##  7 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 01:15:00          12.1             12.1
##  8 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 01:30:00          12.1             12.1
##  9 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 01:45:00          12.1             12.1
## 10 eno_rv_h… 2017-01-02 02:00:00          12.5             12.3
## # ... with 3 more variables: hourly_avg_discharge_cfs &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;,
## #   twelvehr_avg_discharge_cfs &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;, daily_avg_discharge_cfs &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt;

# or use View(discharge_roll) in your RStudio console.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data frame has maintained it’s length (except for the NA columns at the top we deleted using &lt;code&gt;na.omit()&lt;/code&gt;) and there are four new columns with aggregations of discharge at the time scales we specified in our rolling functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can plot this as a hydrograph as we did above or we can also plot each aggregation period against the original 15-min data to see how they compare. Let’s show the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;my_colors &amp;lt;- c(&amp;quot;a_half_hour&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;grey20&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;b_hour&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;grey40&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;c_half_day&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;grey60&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;d_day&amp;quot; = &amp;quot;grey80&amp;quot;)

ggplot(data = discharge_roll) +
  geom_point(aes(x = discharge_cfs,y = halfhr_avg_discharge_cfs, color = &amp;quot;a_half_hour&amp;quot;), size = 1) +
  geom_point(aes(x = discharge_cfs, y = hourly_avg_discharge_cfs, color = &amp;quot;b_hour&amp;quot;), size = 1) +
  geom_point(aes(x = discharge_cfs, y = twelvehr_avg_discharge_cfs, color = &amp;quot;c_half_day&amp;quot;), size = 1) +
  geom_point(aes(x = discharge_cfs, y = daily_avg_discharge_cfs, color = &amp;quot;d_day&amp;quot;), size = 1) +
  facet_wrap(~ site_name, ncol = 1, nrow = 2) +
  scale_color_manual(name = &amp;quot;Time Scale&amp;quot;, values = my_colors) +
  xlab(&amp;quot;15-min Dicharge (cfs)&amp;quot;) +
  ylab(&amp;quot;Aggregated Discharge (cfs)&amp;quot;) +
  theme(panel.grid.major = element_blank(), panel.grid.minor = element_blank(),
        panel.background = element_blank(), axis.line = element_line(colour = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/post/2018-08-04-usgs-rollify_files/figure-html/plot%20aggregated%20time%20scales-1.png&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some interesting patterns that (I think) are worth pointing out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Based on the daily hydrograph we plotted above, the Eno River at Durham (top) data set has higher peak events. This was expected given the daily hydrograph we plotted above. We see that discharge values go up to over 10,000 cfs at the Eno River at Durham site whereas for the Eno River at Hillsborough they only go up to about 5,000 cfs.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting that the half hour and hourly data sets match the 15-min time scale closely; we see the points follow the 1:1 line for both. However, the half day and daily data show dampened responses with lower peaks and skew away from the 1:1 line. This dampening wasn’t completely surprising to me but it made me wonder how this would impact downstream applications of daily streamflow data. Is this dampening represented by a linear or non-linear relationship? Is this relationship a function of watershed properties or near gage properties. Lot’s of questions like this come to mind. Most of which deal with being able to account for and maybe even predict this dampening.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The last thing that I wanted to point out was the spiraling nature of these figures. The more we aggregate the data, the more it seems to spiral into the origin at zero. Also, it’s interesting to compare the overlap of time scale spirals (i.e., half day and daily) between the two gages. More specifically, we see that one ring of the half day and daily spirals overlap for the Eno River at Hillsborough site but we don’t see this overlap at the Eno River at Durham site. I wonder why? Is it because urban development has caused a little more disconnection between water stored in the landscape for the Eno River at Durham site? Do antecedent moisture conditions play a larger role in future stream response in the less developed Eno River at Hillsborough site?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are still so many questions floating around in my head but figuring out how to integrate the &lt;code&gt;tibbletime&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;dataRetrieval&lt;/code&gt; packages has been fun! If you know of any publications that address these questions or just want to say &lt;code&gt;Hi!&lt;/code&gt;, please let me know &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/sheilasaia?lang=en&#34;&gt;via Twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Post</title>
      <link>/post/2018-07-20-my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2018 21:13:14 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-07-20-my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the wateR blog! I’ve been considering starting a water-centric data science blog for a while now. Getting this blogdown website up and running has helped solidify my motivation to write regularly about water-related data science advances that are available to R users…and maybe Python users too (both languages are so useful!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the specific goals of this blog are to (in no special order):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Practice developing my science communication and R skills.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review and demo new packages, data sets, and methods that might be useful to water resources research.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highlight newly published studies that use data science to advance or could be applied to water resources research.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Discuss the present and future of water data science.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interview experts about water-related topics.&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Water Quality in a Suburban Watershed</title>
      <link>/project/mrgp-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/mrgp-project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;R Christie (Mianus River Gorge Preserve), C Nagy (Mianus River Gorge Preserve), MT Walter (Cornell University), PJ Sullivan (Cornell University)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;timeline&#34;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2012-2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-goal&#34;&gt;Project Goal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project was to test two spatial statistics approaches (i.e., kriging based on Euclidian or stream-wise distances) for predicting in-stream waterquality at unsampled locations in the Mianus River near Bedford, NY and Stanford, CT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-links&#34;&gt;Project Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results of this project are currently unpublished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mianus.org/research-and-education/graduate-level/meet-our-raps/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mianus River Gorge Preserve Research Award Program&lt;/a&gt; for supporting this work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phosphorus Cycling in Stream Biofilms</title>
      <link>/project/paos-streams-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/paos-streams-project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PJ Sullivan (Cornell University), JM Regan (Penn State), HJ Carrick (Central Michigan University), AR Buda (USDA-ARS), NA Locke (Penn State), MT Walter (Cornell University)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;timeline&#34;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2014-2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-goal&#34;&gt;Project Goal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project was to test (1) the impact of alternating anaerobic/aerobic conditions on phosphorus cycling in stream biofilms and (2) whether observed patterns mimicked those of polyphosphate accumulating organisms (PAOs) in specialized waste-water treatment plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-links&#34;&gt;Project Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sheilasaia/paper-p-cycling-in-stream-biofilms&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Project GitHub Repository&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/full/10.1086/691439&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Project Peer-Reviewed Publication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.mianus.org/research-and-education/graduate-level/meet-our-raps/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Mianus River Gorge Preserve Research Award Program&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.epa.gov/research-fellowships/science-achieve-results-star-graduate-fellowships&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;EPA STAR Program&lt;/a&gt; for supporting this work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Assessment of Hydrologic Vulnerability to Urbanization and Climate Change in a Rapidly Changing Watershed in the Southeast US</title>
      <link>/publication/yadkin-swat/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/yadkin-swat/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecohydrological Modeling with Stable Isotopes</title>
      <link>/project/stable-isotope-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/stable-isotope-project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;J Archibald, JO Knighton, CK Morris, MT Walter (all at Cornell University)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;timeline&#34;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2016-2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-goal&#34;&gt;Project Goal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project was to develop an ecohydrological model that could be used to test the two-water-world hypothesis presented &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature14983&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-links&#34;&gt;Project Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/SoilWaterLab/JoFlow/tree/Isotope&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;IsoJoFlow Ecohydrology Model&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/hyp.11194&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Project Peer-Reviewed Publication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to J. Evaristo, S Jasechko, and J. McDonnell for their paper that stoked our lab group conversations around this work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Preparing for Climate Change: Using Hydrology Models and Census Data to Map Vulnerable Communities</title>
      <link>/talk/ptrc-climate-may2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/ptrc-climate-may2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This talk is being given by me and Kelly M. Suttles.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract-br&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global climate models project an increase in the frequency and magnitude of storm events in the Southeastern United States in the next several decades. Additionally, urban development in this region is expected to double by 2060 and this growth will likely intensify discrepancies between water supply and demand. Communities unable to prepare for climate-induced changes in water resources may experience adverse social and economic impacts. Given the likely impacts of climate and land use change on water resources, there is a need to (1) develop hydrological models capable of predicting watershed-scale impacts of climate change on water resources in North Carolina, (2) combine hydrological model outputs with demographics data to map communities especially vulnerable to future flooding, and (3) use this information to inform flooding preparedness efforts. We use the Soil Water Assessment Tool (SWAT) to estimate baseline (1982-2002) and future (2050-2070) stream discharge under four climate change scenarios for the Upper Yadkin-Pee Dee Watershed in North Carolina. We then couple SWAT streamflow outputs with social vulnerability index (SoVI) estimates derived from 2010-2014 American Community Survey data. By combining hydrological model outputs and demographics data, we gain insights into how climate change preparedness efforts may serve vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-objectives-br&#34;&gt;Learning Objectives:&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Describe&lt;/strong&gt; the application of hydrological models such as the Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT) to climate change assessments&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summarize&lt;/strong&gt; future climate change impacts for the Upper Yadkin-Pee Dee Watershed region&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illustrate&lt;/strong&gt; how census data and hydrology models can be combined to map vulnerable communities and inform climate change preparedness efforts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sociohydrology in Western North Carolina</title>
      <link>/project/nc-sociohydro-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/nc-sociohydro-project/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h1 id=&#34;collaborators&#34;&gt;Collaborators&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;B Cutts (NC State), R Emanuel (NC State), K Martin (NC State), KM Suttles (USFS), J Vose (USFS), D Wear (USFS), J Coulston (USFS)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;timeline&#34;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2017-current&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-goal&#34;&gt;Project Goal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to combine past and future hydrology model (i.e., &lt;a href=&#34;https://swat.tamu.edu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT)&lt;/a&gt;) outputs with demographics data to create maps and prioritize climate change preparation and adaptation strategies for especially vulnerable communities in Western North Carolina&amp;rsquo;s Upper Yadkin-Pee Dee Watershed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;project-links&#34;&gt;Project Links&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See publication links below.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sheilasaia/paper-yadkin-swat-study&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;GitHub Repository for Suttles et al. 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
GitHub Repository for Saia et al. 2018&amp;hellip;coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;acknowledgements&#34;&gt;Acknowledgements&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://orise.orau.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Oak Ridge Institute for Science and Education&lt;/a&gt; for support this work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Hydrological Models and Census Data to Prioritize Climate Change Preparedness</title>
      <link>/talk/usiale-april2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/usiale-april2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract-br&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global climate models project an increase in the frequency and magnitude of storm events in the Southeastern United States in the next several decades. Additionally, urban development in this region is expected to double by 2060 and this growth will likely intensify discrepancies between water supply and demand. Communities unable to prepare for climate-induced changes in water resources may experience adverse social and economic impacts. Given the likely impacts of climate and land use change on water resources, there is a need to (1) develop hydrological models capable of predicting watershed-scale impacts of climate change on water resources in North Carolina, (2) combine hydrological model outputs with demographics data to map communities especially vulnerable to future flooding, and (3) use this information to inform flooding preparedness efforts. We use the Soil Water Assessment Tool (SWAT) to estimate baseline (1982-2002) and future (2050-2070) stream discharge under four climate change scenarios for the Upper Yadkin-Pee Dee Watershed in North Carolina. We then couple SWAT streamflow outputs with social vulnerability index (SoVI) estimates derived from 2010-2014 American Community Survey data. By combining hydrological model outputs and demographics data, we gain insights into how climate change preparedness efforts may serve vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Hydrological Models and Census Data to Prioritize Climate Change Preparedness</title>
      <link>/talk/unc-feb2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2018 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/unc-feb2018/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract-br&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global climate models project an increase in the frequency and magnitude of storm events in the Southeastern United States in the next several decades. Additionally, urban development in this region is expected to double by 2060 and this growth will likely intensify discrepancies between water supply and demand. Communities unable to prepare for climate-induced changes in water resources may experience adverse social and economic impacts. Given the likely impacts of climate and land use change on water resources, there is a need to (1) develop hydrological models capable of predicting watershed-scale impacts of climate change on water resources in North Carolina, (2) combine hydrological model outputs with demographics data to map communities especially vulnerable to future flooding, and (3) use this information to inform flooding preparedness efforts. We use the Soil Water Assessment Tool (SWAT) to estimate baseline (1982-2002) and future (2050-2070) stream discharge under four climate change scenarios for the Upper Yadkin-Pee Dee Watershed in North Carolina. We then couple SWAT streamflow outputs with social vulnerability index (SoVI) estimates derived from 2010-2014 American Community Survey data. By combining hydrological model outputs and demographics data, we gain insights into how climate change preparedness efforts may serve vulnerable communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecohydrologic considerations for modeling of stable water isotopes in a small intermittent watershed</title>
      <link>/publication/ecohydro-stable-isotope-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/ecohydro-stable-isotope-model/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for polyphosphate accumulating organism (PAO)-mediated phosphorus cycling in stream biofilms under alternating aerobic/anaerobic conditions</title>
      <link>/publication/p-cycling-in-stream-biofilms/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/p-cycling-in-stream-biofilms/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factors Influencing Divergent Patterns of Phosphorus Availability in NY and PA Biogeochemical ‘Hotspots&#39;</title>
      <link>/talk/agu-dec2016/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/agu-dec2016/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;abstract-br&#34;&gt;Abstract:&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anthropogenic alteration of the soil phosphorus (P) cycle leads to subsequent water quality issues in agricultural dominated watersheds. In the humid Northeastern United States (NE US), variably saturated areas can generate surface runoff that transports P and stimulates biogeochemical processes; these hydrologically dynamic locations are often called biogeochemical ‘hotspots’. Many studies have evaluated nitrogen and carbon cycling in biogeochemical hot spots but few have focused on P. We hypothesized seasonally wet parts of the landscape (i.e., hotspots) have smaller biologically available P pools because runoff events frequently carry away nutrients like P. To test this hypothesis, we generated soil wetness index (SWI) maps from soil (SURRGO) and elevation (LiDAR rescaled to 3 m) data and used these maps to direct seasonal soil sampling near Klingerstown, Pennsylvania (PA) and Ithaca, New York (NY). We collected 5cm deep soil samples in PA (bimonthly) and NY (monthly) along soil moisture gradients for a range of land cover types (forest, fallow, and cropped) from May through October. We measured soil moisture in the field and percent organic matter (OM), pH, and three increasingly strong soil P extractions (dilute-salt-extractable P, oxalate-extractable P, and total-extractable P) in the laboratory. Our results indicated a negative relationship between dilute-salt-extractable P concentrations and SWI in PA and no relationship between these same variables in NY. We also found positive relationships between each of the three P extractions in PA but only a positive relationship between oxalate-extractable P and total-extractable P in NY. Our findings in PA support our hypothesis; namely, less biologically available P (i.e. dilute-salt-extractable P) is found in wetter areas of the landscape. However, divergent P availability patterns in NY point to further complexities and confounding variables in our understanding in soil P processes. Further studies will look into the importance of environmental variables such as OM and pH on P patterns under changing soil moisture regimes. The knowledge gained from this study will improve our understanding of P cycling in biogeochemical hotspots and can be used to improve the effectiveness of agricultural management practices in the NE US.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asssessing BMP effectiveness and guiding BMP planning using process-based modeling</title>
      <link>/publication/hct-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/hct-model/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Incorporating pesticide transport into the WEPP model for mulch tillage and no tillage plots with an underlying claypan soil</title>
      <link>/publication/wepp-pesticides-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/wepp-pesticides-model/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
