<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on  </title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on  </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Water Quality in a Suburban Watershed</title>
      <link>/project/mrgp-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/mrgp-project/</guid>
      <description>Collaborators R Christie (Mianus River Gorge Preserve), C Nagy (Mianus River Gorge Preserve), MT Walter (Cornell University), PJ Sullivan (Cornell University)
Timeline 2012-2015
Project Goal The goal of this project was to test two spatial statistics approaches (i.e., kriging based on Euclidian or stream-wise distances) for predicting in-stream waterquality at unsampled locations in the Mianus River near Bedford, NY and Stanford, CT.
Project Links Results of this project are currently unpublished.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Phosphorus Cycling in Stream Biofilms</title>
      <link>/project/paos-streams-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/paos-streams-project/</guid>
      <description>Collaborators PJ Sullivan (Cornell University), JM Regan (Penn State), HJ Carrick (Central Michigan University), AR Buda (USDA-ARS), NA Locke (Penn State), MT Walter (Cornell University)
Timeline 2014-2015
Project Goal The goal of this project was to test (1) the impact of alternating anaerobic/aerobic conditions on phosphorus cycling in stream biofilms and (2) whether observed patterns mimicked those of polyphosphate accumulating organisms (PAOs) in specialized waste-water treatment plants.
Project Links Project GitHub Repository Project Peer-Reviewed Publication</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ecohydrological Modeling with Stable Isotopes</title>
      <link>/project/stable-isotope-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/stable-isotope-project/</guid>
      <description>Collaborators J Archibald, JO Knighton, CK Morris, MT Walter (all at Cornell University)
Timeline 2016-2017
Project Goal The goal of this project was to develop an ecohydrological model that could be used to test the two-water-world hypothesis presented here.
Project Links IsoJoFlow Ecohydrology Model Project Peer-Reviewed Publication
Acknowledgements Thanks to J. Evaristo, S Jasechko, and J. McDonnell for their paper that stoked our lab group conversations around this work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sociohydrology in Western North Carolina</title>
      <link>/project/nc-sociohydro-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/nc-sociohydro-project/</guid>
      <description>Collaborators B Cutts (NC State), R Emanuel (NC State), K Martin (NC State), KM Suttles (USFS), J Vose (USFS), D Wear (USFS), J Coulston (USFS)
Timeline 2017-current
Project Goal The goal of this project is to combine past and future hydrology model (i.e., Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT)) outputs with demographics data to create maps and prioritize climate change preparation and adaptation strategies for especially vulnerable communities in Western North Carolina&amp;rsquo;s Upper Yadkin-Pee Dee Watershed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hydrologic Characterization Tool (HCT)</title>
      <link>/project/hct-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2011 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/hct-project/</guid>
      <description>Collaborators J Boll (Washington State University Pullman), ES Brooks (University of Idaho), Z Easton (Virginia Tech), L Kurkalova (North Carolina Ag &amp;amp; Tech), B Rittenburg (Univesrity of Idaho), A Squires (University of Idaho), TS Steenhuis (Cornell University), G Vellidis (University of Georgia), JD Wulfhorst (University of Idaho)
Timeline 2007-2011
Project Goal The goal of this project was to use an exisiting process-based model (i.e., the USDA WEPP model to develop a web-based hydrologic characterization tool (HCT) that could be used by water resources managers to evaluate the impact of agricultural best management practices on water quality (i.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>